Guide to the Records of the Research Institute for the Study of Man's (RISM) Cross-Cultural Comparisons of Aging and Longevity Study RISM.RG.15
New York University Archives
Records of the Research Institute for the Study of Man's (RISM) Cross-Cultural Comparisons of Aging and Longevity Study (The Longevity Study)
1962-1995
New York University Archives
Research Institute for the Study of Man
RISM.RG.15
16.5 Linear Feet in 27 boxes
Separated Materials
Funding contracts have been removed from the collection and will be retained by the Research Institute for the Study of Man.
Related Materials
See also the Sula Benet Papers, RISM RG 2.
Arrangement
These records have been arranged into eight series:
I. Researchers II. Correspondence with Universities III. Manuscripts/Publications IV. Conferences V. US/USSR Materials VI. Progress Reports/Research/Funding VII. Oversize Material VIII. Unorganized Papers and Articles
The collection is organized into eight series
I. Researchers
II. Correspondence with Universities
III. Manuscripts/Publications
IV. Conferences
V. US/USSR Materials
VI. Unorganized Papers and Articles
VII. Index Cards, Research and Oversized
VIII. Progress Reports, Research and Funding
Appendix
Scope and Content
In 1970, at the invitation of the USSR Academy of Sciences, ethnographer Dr. Sula Benet began extensive field studies in the Caucasian region of Abkhasia, Russia. Her goal was to investigate Abkhasian lifeways after fifty years of collectivization. Over the next few years, Dr. Benet's study generated numerous publications, including How to Live to be 100, considered a landmark publication on gerontological research. Following her retirement from Hunter College in 1973, Dr. Benet became a Senior Fellow of the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM), in New York City.
Fluent in Russian, Polish, and Ukrainian, Dr. Benet's areas of specialization included cultural anthropology among the Slavic cultures of Eastern Europe where she conducted field work from 1945-1973, sponsored by Columbia University, the Social Science Research Council, RISM, and the Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research. Dr. Benet also conducted studies in culture and personality, as well as aging and longevity.
Based on Dr. Benet's research in Russia, Dr. Vera Rubin, director of RISM, proposed that Dr. Benet undertake a major study of the long-living people who had been her chief Abkhasian subjects. Dr. Benet's study led to the development of a US-USSR multidisciplinary research project on longevity, which involved both Soviet and American social scientists. The study was known as the Cross-Cultural Comparisons of Aging and Longevity Study.
Access Restrictions
Some restricted materials pertaining mainly to internal finances, administration and private information remain at the Reed Foundation and are closed to researchers.
Rubin, Vera D.; Benet, Sula, 1903-1982; Comitas, Lambros; Lees, Francis C.; Wolf, David J.
- Series I: Researchers
  - American Resumes, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Soviet Curriculum Vitae, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - William Bowerman, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chad Gordon, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Samuel A. Corson (papers), 1980s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Isabella Geriatric Center, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Center for Geriatrics and Gerontology, Columbia University, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Documents, 1976-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interested Individuals, 1977-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ongoning Studies on Aging, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - US-USSR Longevity Project (correspondence), 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - University of Pittsburgh Gerontology Center, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alvin W. Wolfe, University of Southern Florida, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Charles L. Rose, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Academy of Sciences - Moscow, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series II: Correspondence with Universities
  - Materials for USSR Trip, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bio-Medical Test Form, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - University of Kentucky - New Materials, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - University of Kentucky - Research Foundation, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - University of Kentucky - Site Visit, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - USSR/Kentucky Research (SIA), 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sanders-Brown Center - News, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Anthropometry - University of Kentucky proposal, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - University of Kentucky - Correspondence, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Kentucky Trip, 1978 September (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - David Wolf, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Kentucky Papers (Sent to Florida), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - University of Kentucky - Abstracting Forms, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Phillip Drucker Obituary, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Courier Journal Magazine, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Application to John E. Fogarty International Health Center, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Ageing Among the Scots-Irish of Northeastern Kentucky - Revised Application to NIA, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Addenda For: Ageing Among the Scots-Irish of Northeastern Kentucky, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda of Agreement, 1977-1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - University of Kansas - Newsletter, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - University of Kansas - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series III: Manuscripts/Publications (by author name) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts (by author name)
    - Gogokhia, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Ferrell and Salamatina, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Chebotarev, et al, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Dalakishvili, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Grigorov, et al, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Kobychev, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Dalakishvili, Circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Introduction - Longevity, 2nd Symposium, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Zubov and Kozlov I-1, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Kozlov and Komarova I-2, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Pavlenko I-3, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Smirnova I-4, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Krupnik I-5, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Komarova and Bolshakov I-6, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Bloshakov, Brook and Kozlov I-7, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Kozlov and Krasnikova I-8, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Inal-IPA I-9, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Komarov and Bolshakov - Demographic Aspects of Research on Longevity, 1983-1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Kopeshavidze - Traditional Diet, Circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, Circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, Circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Draft Manuscripts
    - Draft Publications, 1980s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX) Publications
    - IREX Publications, 1972-1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - IREX, Correspondence and Articles, 1970s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - IREX Publications, 1984-1989 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - IREX Publications, 1980s (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - IREX/Victor Kozlov, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Russian Manuscripts and Articles
    - Kiev, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Russian Manuscripts and Articles, Circa 1980s (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Manuals and Bibliography
    - Health - Illness, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Anthropometry, Circa 1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Demography - Birth/Death Records, Circa 1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Aging and Longevity Manual, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Manual for Cross-Cultural Comparisons of Aging and Longevity, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Bibliography of the Manual for Cross-Cultural Comparisons of Aging and Longevity, circa 1979 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Bibliography of the Manual for Cross-Cultural Comparisons of Aging and Longevity, circa 1979 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Printout of the US-USSR Binational Project: Anthropological Aspects of Aging and Longevity, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - The Longevity Project, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Proceedings of the 1st Joint US-USSR Symposium on Aging and Longevity, Circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Proceedings of the 1st Joint US-USSR Symposium on Aging and Longevity, Circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Proceedings of the 1st Joint US-USSR Symposium on Aging and Longevity, Circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Proceedings of the 1st Joint US-USSR Symposium on Aging and Longevity, Circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Proceedings of the 1st Joint US-USSR Symposium on Aging and Longevity, Circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Proceedings of the 1st Joint US-USSR Symposium on Aging and Longevity, Circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Proceedings of the 1st Joint US-USSR Symposium on Aging and Longevity, Circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - University of Kenticky Human Investigations and Studies Sub-Committee, Visa Requests, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Update on Soviet-American Relations, No. 4, 1984 October (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Conferences
  - Abstracts (Working Papers), Undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Symposium Abstracts, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Francis C. Lees, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Kvasnikov, et al, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Kozlov and Komarova - Geography of Longevity, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Krupnik - Leaderships (Russian), 1981 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Korkusko - Lung Function (Russian), 1981 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - A Many-Faceted Biological-Anthropological and Social-Ethnographic Analysis of National Groups and Ethnic Groups with a High Percentage of Dolgozhiteli (Long-Lived People), Undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Introduction, Vera Rubin, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Norakadze and Bakhtadze, Personality, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Pavlenko, Growth Categories (Russian), 1981 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Pavlovski, Bone Structure, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Salamatina, et al Genetic Study, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Smirnova, et al, Physical Anthropology, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Smirnova, et al, Family Types, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Starovoitova, Ethnography, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Volkov-Dubrovin, et al, Russian Physical Anthropological, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Zubov and Kozlov - Complex Project, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Sula Benet, 1980-1981 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Soviet Symposium Papers, 1980-1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Gashinova - State of Dentition, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - INAL - IAP Folklore, Undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Grigorov, et al, Nutrition, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Chebotarev, et al, Physical Condition and CBS, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Bugaev - Physical Work Capacity, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Miklashevskaya, et al, Somatic Development of Children, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Mankovski, Mintz, et al, Genealogical Aspects, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - English Translation of Soviet Memorandum on RISM Manuel, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Thomas Arcury, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Craig Tussey, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - John van Willigen, Circa 1980 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - David Wolf, 1980-1983 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - University of Kentucky - Papers Publication by IREX, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Clippings - Vera Rubin, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Lebedinskaya - Soft Facial Tissue, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Dalakishvili, et al, Phyisco Chemical, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Garsevanishvili - Physical Development Children, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Kozlov - Introduction, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Proceedings of the First Joint US-USSR Symposuim, volume 1, circa 1982 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Conferences (First Symposium), circa 1981 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - NIA Correspondence, 1977-1982 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Second US-USSR Symposium Proposal (NIA), 1981-1982 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - National Institute on Aging, 1977-1983 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - National Institute on Aging, 1977-1981 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - NIA Site Visit, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Council on Aging Proposed Reviews, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Aging Review Committee documents, correspondence, etc., undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Summary Statement NIA, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Second Symposium Publication, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Second Symposium Publication, 1980s (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Publication: Maps, Figures, etc., circa 1980 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Longevity Article Drafts, circa 1980s (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Transparencies, 1983-1984 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Abbasov, Kozlov, Namasov, 1983-1985 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Bolshakov, Brook, Kozlov, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Bolshakov, Brook, Kozlov, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Bugaev and Stezhenskaya, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Chebotarev, et al, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Kozlov and Krasnikova, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Sula Benet Abstract, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Symposium, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - World Anthropology Working Paper on Aging, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Longevity Lecture - Columbia University, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - 1982 World Assembly on the Elderly (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Series V: US/USSR Material
  - VC/LC Trip to Soviet Union, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Soviet Trip, Comitas, Benet, et al, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Soviet Union Visit, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Soviet Union Visit, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Soviet Union Visit, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Soviet Union Visit, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Academy of Sciences USSR Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Technical Manual, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Academy of Sciences Collaboration, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Trip to the Soviet Union, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Update on Sovet Relations, no. 8, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Center for Defense Information, undated (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Technical Materials for the Soviet Union, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - USSR Longevity Articles, 1970s-1980s (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Soviet Ethnographers-US Relations, 1980-1981 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Soviet Research Program, undated (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Journals, 1980-1981 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence and Documents Soviet Union, 1975-1976 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Kiev, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Soviet Manuscript, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Soviet Visit to New York, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Notes - RISM Visit to Soviet Union, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Soviet Union Trip (Rubin, Benet, Crawford), 1977 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Soviet Visit, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Lees/Wolf/van Willigen visit to Soviet Union, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Benet's Trip to the Soviet Union, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Soviet Visit, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Dr. S.I. Brook, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Dr. V.I. Kozlov, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Soviet Visit to US, Dalakishvili, Gogokhia, Salamatina, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - 2017 Accretion: Conferences on Aging, 1981-1982 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - 2017 Accretion: Correspondence with Soviet Scholars, 1987 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - 2017 Accretion: Funding Resources, 1978 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - 2017 Accretion: Inquiries for Aging Reseach, 1977-1982 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - 2017 Accretion: Notes, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 25, Folder 5-7)
  - 2017 Accretion: Research Protocol Progress Report, 1977 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - 2017 Accretion: Research Protocol, 1980-1985 (Box 25, Folder 9-13)
  - 2017 Accretion: Proceedings of the First Joint US-USSR Symposium on Agin and Longevity, 1981 (Box 26, Folder 1-2)
  - 2017 Accretion: Notes and Working Papers for Second US-USSR Symposium on Aging and Longevity, 1982 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - 2017 Accretion: Correspondence on Second US-USSR Symposium on Aging and Longevity, 1980-1982 (Box 26, Folder 4-6)
  - 2017 Accretion: Second US-USSR Symposium on Longevity: Research in the Caucasus, 1982 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - 2017 Accretion: Third Meeting of the American Council of Learned Societies - Soviet Academy of Sciences, 1979 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - 2017 Accretion: RISM Reception for Drs. Semyon Dalakishuil, Shota Gogkhia, and Naira Salamatina, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - 2017 Accretion: "Introduction" Manuscript by Vera Rubin, undated (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - 2017 Accretion: "Morphological Description of Abkhazians of Ochamchira District (Chlou Village)" by A.P. Pestryakov, 1981 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - 2017 Accretion: "Morphologial Traits of Dental Systems of Abkhasians from Chlou Village in Connection with the Phenomenon of Longevity" by G.A. Aksyanova, 1981 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - 2017 Accretion: "Notes on Folk Medicine in the Ochamchir Region" by M.B. Dzanelidze and D.N. Aneli, 1981 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - 2017 Accretion: V.I. Kozlov Letter to the Editor of Gerontologist, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 14)
- Series VI: Unorganized Papers and Articles
  - Papers and Articles (Articles A-Z), 1969-1981 (Box 19)
  - Papers and Articles (Periodicals and Reference Manual Drafts), 1971-1979 (Box 20)
  - Papers and Articles (Periodicals and Journals), 1977-1982 (Box 21)
  - Papers and Articles (Articles and Reprints), 1970s (Box 22)
  - 2017 Accretion: Newspaper Clippings, 1977-1982 (Box 27, Folder 1)
- Series VII: Index Cards, Research and Oversized
  - Index Cards and Research, circa 1970s (Box 23)
  - Sula Benet Article, 1972 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Our Elders: A Generation Neglected, Record and Teacher's Guide, 1972 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Index Cards, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Appendix
  - [Map of the USSR], undated
  - [Stavropolskikrai]
  - Older Americans in the US by Counties, Government Printing Office, photocopy, 1970
  - Azerbaidzhanian Zoogeographical Map (2), Institute of Georgraphy, Academy of Sciences, Azerbaidzhan SSR, 1963
  - Georgian Zoogeographical Map (2), Vakhushti Geographical Institute, Georgian Academy of Sciences, Tbilisi, undated
  - [Map of Georgia], undated
  - Older Americans in the US by counties, Government Printing Office, 1960